all right welcome to active infrance
stream number 8.1 it's December 15
2024 I'm going to start with a GitHub
push to the GitHub
repo active inference Institute
slstart while we have meanwhile cursor
current version
0.43 translating curricula in the
background visualizing learning
paths having our agenda up so thanks for
joining if you're watching live
definitely write some interesting things
in the chat and I'll look to reans it
into the stream all right here we are
symbols greetings good evening
Jeff again this is in GitHub repository
active inference Institute start
the idea here was to build on some prior
perplexity and llm based methods that
we've worked on in different projects
earlier in the year and kind of continue
with this all by all theme across
domains and backgrounds intersecting
with onboarding and curricula for active
inference this is more than just a
translation tool it's a framework for
understanding and optimizing how
knowledge flows through different
perspectives modular treatment of topics
and perspectives enables flexible
application
okay so first where are we headed to in
terms of the output then let's look at
the scripts that are using perplexity
even now to go through it so the written
curricula are in English and then
they're being translated in chunks to
other language so
here's a synthetic bi ologist
background introduction curriculum to
active inference translated into
Japanese and this
is more than 1,400 lines
long that's what it looks like in
cursor let's reload the
repo it's still writing this very large
initial push we'll look at what the
markdowns look like in a few minutes
that's the translated curriculum um the
written curricula there's two sets of
audiences that we'll Trace back to that
it's drawing upon the First with just
their names are individual specific
people or different audience profile
we'll get to how that's specified like a
high school student and a middle school
student so these are different audiences
or different synthetic
knowledge domains that are constructed
we'll again look into them like cooking
so this is a complete curriculum
implicitly in English for somebody in
the cooking
industry conduct workshops where
participants develop new recipes using
active inference
algorithms predicting food safety
risks those are the different domains so
this uh pipeline that we we're about to
go
through uses perplexity
doai large language model
llm interface API to do research on
entities
specific or groups of
entities and different synthetic domains
we'll look at how they're defined
those researches those are done in step
one step two write introductions again
going to call perplexity to write out
those curricula in chunks in
English three does visualization of a
few different kinds on those generated
curricula four translates
into languages right now these languages
are uncommented out there's more
languages you can just comment uh or
uncomment I will show my
perplexity balance at the beginning of
the stream and then we'll
see how
much it changes on during the
stream okay
$67 68 in the perplexity Bank
using the
small here on their suggest uh model
card
page I'm using the Llama 3.1 sonar small
online this is the same context length
as these more larger parameter models
just from short testing though it's
faster and it's cheaper
so 67
okay all
right so where we're going is this V now
let's look at the visualizations on
those curricula from step three then
look at
the
script
okay first metric so this is four each
of
those it's just translating chunks in
the background that could be
multi-threaded but it can also cause
more API trouble than it's worth okay so
this is for each is a comma
separated
file open it in Libre office
this is some word count
information on in the sections and the
paragraphs descriptive statistics on
curriculum
metric this
file is some summary statistics on those
37 written curricula
in terms of the mean and the average and
all of that of those descriptive
statistics
metrics distribution.png has those
descriptive document statistics for
those 37
curricula okay content
analysis this is principal component
analysis PCA analysis
on
13 cumulative percent of the variance in
the term
frequency so it's interesting that the
entities are all clustered more closely
clustered over here or at least some of
them key
Concepts top 20 Concepts word
cloud similarity matrices with
hierarchical
clustering so here that this um
dendrogram does sort of visually and at
the hierarchy
monopile uh topological clustering
method confirming this cluster for
example some or there's this
relationship Logistics
with whatever it
is spatial we
topic
distribution this looks like the uh rows
are the loading in the different 37
curricula the
topics are top top seven topics and
their presentation across interesting
that Shaka Works in Fashion and so
there's a connection with the fabric we
can see if that pops up again
different topic okay and topic
summaries topic one so this is the one
that has this loading across these
different
fields okay then
there's concept maps and learning paths
here's the concept
Maps these are just starting points all
of these are just
starting point draft outputs but they
can be updated from the underlying
information so here's for Chris
fields for the curricula generated for
Chris
Fields this is a igen vector
centrality Network topic
graph in different communities
high school student concept map let's
see this
one free energy principle looks like
it's in this one Orange Community
variational minimize inference Active
Energy there's the blue neural biology
decision organismal tool
making may maybe these have used maybe
not Middle School student
but cool
nonetheless that's concept map and here
are learning
paths these are just okay we'll see how
this one's looks like a
very example applications are Central
connected this Hubb and spoke M way to
the these high school student
path
H somebody with a background in ATM
transactions AI powered
ATMs case study 2 personalized user
interface
biology
graph Bucky
Fuller
ephemeralization bi
mimicry
cooking data on flavor profiles and
ingredient interaction
actions food safety
training predict the flavor profile for
a given combination of
ingredients
entomology insect behavior and biology
so at least in the ballpark those are
the metaanalysis
visualizations let's just look at one of
those written curricula files then into
the scripts so let's look at
video
games let's see if the GitHub push is
done okay yeah write any questions or
write a topic in the chat I'll try to
reenter
it let's look at high school
students and video game
high school students in
2025 Source high school student
worldview
H key knowledge gaps cultural linguistic
considerations conceptual Bridges so
this top part okay now getting into some
topics
predictive
coding further reading learning
pathway learning environment
okay and this is
for now let's see the video
game game design
game mechanics narrative design user
experience
agile
[Music]
programming game integrating active
inference into game
development Dynamic difficulty
adjustment mental health same example
used in the high school
case here's the curriculum content so
it's about it's two and it's it's it's
separate in two there's
the domain
analysis and then there's the curriculum
content and then they're just
concatenated to get that marked down so
here's the curriculum
itself so let's see that has welcome
message relevance value
proposition connection to existing
domain knowledge overview of Learning
Journey success stories and ex examples
conceptual foundations core active
inference Concepts using domain
analogies mathematical principles with
domain relevant examples practical
applications and domain context
integration with existing domain
Frameworks case studies in the
domain Dynamic difficulty adjustment
narrative
generation for gaming interactive
examples and
exercises some of these interactive ones
are TBD but at least they're scoped
there technical framework mathematical
formalization using domain notation
that's kind of interesting maybe you
could use the letter set or domain of
some given uh
config computational aspects with domain
tools utilize game engines such as
Unreal Engine or Unity for integrating
AI driven
mechanics implementation considerations
practical applications domain specific
use case
implementation Advanced topics br
computer interface virtual reality
augmented reality BCI VR AR research
Direction collaboration
possibility further
readings books practical implementation
steps
addressing potential questions
conclusion
references
okay let's just briefly look at that for
Blake and then look at the
scripts all right
districts let's look at how some of the
translations
look translated
curriculum
Russian synthetic biology
okay these sections are
empty
repeating
English back to Russian English
code
Russian back to English
okay Hindi
language somebody with the RSA
cryptographic
background okay
repeating not filling out sections this
could just be a prompt to error doing
the Json or um nuanced approaches to
documents blocks of Dos these kinds of
approaches that'll add a lot of value
this is the Big Blob method the all
byall folder script
method okay here are the
scripts okay there's two scripts with a
beginning prefix onecore research domain
and research entity so there's domain
and entity folders each of these script
script Ones Will iterate over the
markdown files in the synthetic domains
and within each entity
subfolder just the
py so the idea here is whether it's a
purely synthetic
python I just say generate statements
looking like a high school
student from chrisf fields. py or just
fields. py
format and then those B version so
that's the pure synthetic uh llm based
approach there's also generating
transcripts from videos so these were
like transcripts from Chris Fields
giving different lectures different
papers different podcast
appearances could have one to many could
be all the literature of a researcher it
could be their they could bring in their
private nodes what could be using a
local llm or none generate these py that
are used so the py are the pseudo
code uh quote this is not a py file
representations of
key attributes quotes perspectives it
can be written in structured list so
basically just a bullet point list all
the way on through having here for Carl
first I think there's some numerical
estimates or some pan psychism 7 so then
it can have also these other
expressivity with with the pseudo code
at the semantic layer or these could
interface with they could have some sort
of schema to be used in a more
structured way as well and and these are
just transcripts and other things that
are dropped into a folder markdowns and
then just within here given the
markdowns in this
folder add comprehensive accurate
statements to this py that's that's what
is um like the entity specific or the
audience specific payload or context is
the single py in each of these
subfolders whereas for the
domains these domains um there's for for
the context here there's basically two
kinds there's free energy principle and
active
inference MD which is just examples
facts explanations
definitions facts questions about active
inference and about other domains so
here's the synthetic hopter so a b is
wasps and softes and then to to add on
to this just I'll use control I to use
the agent mode in the current cursor so
this is only available to at this time I
believe the anthropic
models but it it uses specific specific
code functions and it can do a few
different interesting things so early
days for this but pretty cool so here
add
questions accurate facts examples
information on the I'm off
here so I can be done from a
blank slide rank
blank text file
uh or it can be versioned like more and
this could also be in adjacent format or
it could be the export from a
database but just having these
semantic little nuggets and
examples so let's see how it edits
synthetic hop okay so now it's
adding adding
sections keep questions about hop
scientific facts Advanced behaviors in
hop evolutionary adaptations in hopa
conservation environmental impact
so human interactions with hopa so that
would be included the next time that um
script one is run and when script one is
run it outputs into these domain and
audience research files the output is as
both a Jason and a
markdown this
request let's look at the prompt in
one
says
generate gen Analyze This domain content
and identify aspects of Their audience
characteristics Analyze This domain
content to understand the typical
industry professionals background
knowledge and
perspective according to these
structured responses for that domain so
this is the research domain the research
entity
question says generate a comprehensive
analysis for this audience and also it
can inject in the
FP factual information itself to or you
know I'm saying factual just in the
sense of
empirical from what can can be version
right
here so both of
those um output these research reports
so here's the high school student
research report this is the background
analysis so it's just
researching the the different
characteristics and situation for
communicating with the average
professional from that domain or that
audience about active inference
okay that's one two so here also go to
this code viz cool
tool so this is the code
viz uh code
analysis let's do it on
two um I hope
it's let's get redo it for
here yeah help us fully analyze
code visualization
tool
meanwhile okay it loads in the API
key um okay
so let's look at the graphical
flow API key is is loaded with this
function file is loaded with this this
function load
file extract
sections
extracts subsections from these
different splitting
signals generate section prompt takes
that chunk its name and its content and
the Fe
information
and responds to that section's need
given the FP content
with these constraints create a thorough
version so this
concatenates this is the Mad Lib The
prepr Prompt that concatenates the
information and gives a format again
there's other ways to do this get get
perplexity
response
calls the perplexity API again using the
Llama 3.1 small sonar small
save section saves one
section concatenate section puts them
back together save complete
curriculum saves the concatenated output
process research file um iterates
through the sections here's the main so
this is what is going to be now
visualized in the
graph logging setup
occurs script directory
and the llm keys are pointed
to base directory for future file
references is named audience in the
domain those two different research
directories the location of the FP o in
information and the output
Direction the directories are made that
need to be made
so set up logging Main initializes set
up
loging let's see if these other methods
so these are just
definitions complexity
API is
called perplexity API is loaded that's
the next function that's
called process the research
file with these
methods extract the section parse
markdown content into discrete
curriculum section for
processing for each section
extracted generate the section prompt
make the
concatenated uh query to be sent to
perplexity that is
the um Mad Lib component that's being
iterated over and the ACM FP factual
part empirical
part and the format output component and
the system prompt but that's the same
for all here
that prepr prompt or whatever we call it
concatenated final payload assembled is
sent through the get perplexity
response that passes then to the save
file
operations and here are the outputs
so kind of cool I'm sure there's other
ways to use this really
interestingly we can cop it in copy it
in different formats there mermaid
format
there okay so that's two it it goes
through the sections
of the personalized curriculum
overview and then seeks to generate that
material
let's analyze the
next
number
three uh well four is another perplexity
script this one as alluded to earlier
there's a Target languages at the Top If
it's uncommented it'll be iterated over
so that's what happening right now
is synthetic astronomy German
language here on the synthetic astronomy
run then it'll do Russian Portuguese
sili toolik and then uncommon or comment
the ones that you want iterated
over this is some font
mapping this has
analogous mad living curriculum content
in English maybe for some languages it
would be better to just go direct to the
language
two but here there there can be a repeat
it could be a curated of one and shifted
to another um format content and
language and the
chunking into 4,000
characters okay let's look at the code
viz on three
okay collects the curricula
pre-processes them analyzes their
content generates the descriptive
statistic
metrics on curricula over
curriculum here's a dependency check for
the visualization
components here's a decorator for
plotting
safely plot safely decorator at plot
safely this is a decorator being applied
to plot content
analysis plot safely applied to plot
learning paths
plot concept
Maps those are the three folders that
are
shown in the beginning curriculum
visualizations there's the metrics
initial output then there's these three
plot safely sections concept ma content
analysis learning paths
okay looks like it's still processing
the
three let's do another GitHub push add a
few more
languages push to GitHub
6768 reloading perplexity seeing how
much just this one thread of continuous
chugging with the so that was
a
65 cents USD from having one thread
continually run for however long that
was so couple dollars an hour for one
thread and each
let's just do it the llm way copy in
some
logs chat how long does
each of
these Claude 3.5 Sonic 2024 1022 coming
through so between 9 and 23
seconds and there are probably better
translation
models
okay this one's still
processing maybe it'll get there if
you're watching live though ask a
question otherwise I'll just sort of
review everything
okay so to
review where this is at what can it do
well we can learn a lot by putting in
specific or general entities or domains
it could be the people at this
conference at this exact time MD it
could be entity in
organization it could be a specific
person at an organization or a group at
an organization you you you can add your
own using whatever background supporting
files projected onto a Pui
synthetic
domains entities research
them the research prompt could be
extended or or the research output could
be used even by itself it's in the
domain
research in the Json and the
markdown two right introduction
splits the
personalized domain or audience
research and writes that curriculum for
them resulting in the written
curricula so again here's let's go to
the high school
student written
curricula high school
student versionable
curricula and research on bridging to
their background or
situation people can continue to to
update this and add you know sub high
schools that's analyzed in
three
visually and translated in four
so hopefully these are useful starting
points by themselves they're just files
you can
download uh and send to somebody you can
use the GitHub repo
slstart to request collaboration access
make a merge and PLL all that fun stuff
become a
collaborator
um this was kind of it's all in the
languages
folder so we could have some other top
level folders of course this is just a
new repo so lots of ways we
can go with
it um I'll look now to the to-do but if
anyone's watching live wants to make a
comment or a request otherwise I'll go
to the
to-do organize a few of those add a few
more things that have come up see what
anyone writes in the
chat um
okay
okay researcher integration Implement
orci ID API integration or CID and other
identity API
Integrations get research profile
information on researchers in open-
Source databases
have data interfaces visual interfaces
for people adding
information publication scraping of
course we're
legal research domain
analysis this could be using
perplexity with internet to to look for
other context on the fields of
somebody's research as as scraped and
submitted could could be some
other research design researcher profile
structure so this is maybe where it
could connect with something like a
within or across organizational platform
different user
profiles validations okay so this is
developing
researcher
entity
domains
researchers so that's the
first improve are handling and
structuring and
Ingress and accounting for of entity
audience information and synthetic
domain
information database
implementation got
clarify design
and clarify SL documents database
schema entity relationships works at of
co-authored with metadata structure
version control
system so versioning
information uh how knowing which
person's information was used for which
input to which model what
parameterization at what time Etc
Implement database
connectors uh not sure what scale some
of this query optimization and caching
becomes relevant and economical probably
eventually d validation definitely
important okay so this has to do with
having a better structured instead of
the the all by all blob by
blob folder by folder inch by inch
approach
here having some better structured
database and and I guess it goes into
it here in phase three
which let's just look at that one use
Fabric or maybe
another maybe another agent
orchestration or kind of computing or
task framework but one of the previous
streams used
Fabric and and there there there may be
others too research here but again use
that database with more of an expressive
pattern
language templated procedural
operational
nuanced approach like if we only want to
do one language and one background right
now the fastest way to do it is to
comment out all the languages except for
that one in the file and then remove
temporarily uh temporarily everything
from the domains and the entities except
for the one that you wanted but but that
might work to get one done but if we
wanted to have each of them done in a
custom way then having some more
expressive
reproducible
composable
uh pre-rendering layer for these
operational traces that would be
important back to phce two here as it
laid out application extensions okay
organizational
support organizational configuration
system so different templates maybe
having a single config
folder with its own versioning where the
The Branding or the
logo or the Styles and the document
formats for a given organization could
all be handled there so it sort of could
be plug-and playay and separate out the
entity background for example from
the uh organization config and this is
more like an interactive interface
Direction but to build out better some
of these analytics and
visualizations within an across
curricula and then have a static output
dashboards or interactive dashboards
using some kind of business intelligence
tool use catechism framework templated
structure question answer answer
format grant writing system so this gets
more into the um document
genre modular
writing composition
writing with human and llm and all that
uh
happening okay phase
three that was the uh pattern languages
for more expressive task execution model
Improvement more expressive model so
that could be a better um it could be
using the perplexity API with a
different call it could be replacing
that with some other
analogous um
llm uh a colleague has provided me some
information on uh using it but if
somebody wants to
help update these
methods so that they call some other
longer context window uh llm or
something then just make make the
change multimodal support that could be
really interesting making and receiving
images yeah parallelization memory
management wasn't an issue on this old
laptop with cursor because the llms were
via perplexity but maybe at some scale
uh interactive live
demo interactive
tutorials Community
features monitoring and maintenance
resource usage reporting
dashboard
documentation okay prioritization and
some notes
yeah pretty interesting what it comes up
with let's improve the documentation a
little
bit and then see if anyone writes
something interesting in the
chat and then maybe do some one other
random feature and then call it for this
one develop and
Improvement and
add concise new accurate information
directly in best sections
to this R
Me
Oh I thought we were talking about
synthetic common opter let's see where
goes with it though and then we'll
return to the
reading that was with control I composer
while that one's going chat improve at
read
me adding new accurate
sections so even though it's like in the
same
window they're
different composer is a little
better okay
accept
it now
make
thoughtful
contributive accurate additions to read
me for how far we've gotten
and only that far
the chat little bit of back and forth in
and out of the
code
sections composer I found just doesn't
get into those sorts of issues bug
finder this looks funny I think it's it
uses a custom cost so it one time it
estimated it at like $30 to do this it's
like there's bugs for free
outside and the code okay now updating
the read me
okay focusing a little bit on the hopter
but okay current
domain so this is like very hopter
related not very helpful for the read me
reject it start a new composer
Trace reindex cursor
sometimes it it it does it on its own
other times just to double
check okay and then let's also do read
me finish
hello Aubrey
Walters okay this python virtualization
is probably not needed so that's a
little bit
invented m
not useful
information I like the built with
heart really just always shows it's just
such a fractal
ride sometimes it's so good sometimes it
it really can be Insidious over
different time scales
these parts were
accurate
yeah I hope that
people find the primary artifacts to be
useful like if you have a friend
uh
who is of a certain expertise and a
certain
language then it's not if it's not
already
here uh add it to one of the scripts or
make the
request so that you can send
uh translated curriculum just sends okay
here's a bunch of different backgrounds
in Portuguese for somebody who wants to
use
that so I'll continue to let this
one run for
now um probably doing a multi-threaded
or some other way would be better or for
some of the languages it seems to be
leaving a significant uh number of
blanks so maybe I won't um do all of it
let's
just do one sort of semi manual llm so
here
translate read me into
Spanish output
in me Spanish
okay the documents folder move in the
Stream
agenda and do one
baseball Yep looks
pretty cool
o
okay so I was just translating it into
one language
manually push
GitHub all
right now in
baseball for edification
and
more please help write
intricate
imbricated deep lore for
Baseball American
1920s memorable
moments describing the at read me and
all it
entails for
this
given where it is all comma all
at let's see what format it does and
then we'll say
um
continue continue to make
more crystallin and preent
and accurate deep lore specifics
specifications Min
particulars for
more baseball deep
lore
and specific reference with the read me
and
FP synthetic quote all by
all folder script kitty
style terminal
interface synthetic intelligence in the
format of long quote who's on first
F okay let's see but
it has
some knowledge graph analysis of the
1920s in baseball okay that will be
useful metric analysis baseball's
Quantum
Leap batting average
contextualization home run frequency
analysis pitching Effectiveness metrics
Fielding position
Evolution hm
okay getting
there distill the entire
dialogue
retaining all
the Galt and specifics
only entirely being in the quote who's
on
first style of
dialogue all details must be retained
and with
more linguistic cultural
baseball esoterica and actuality
this dialogue serves as a meta
commentary on how baseball's complexity
mirrors the fun
FAL principles of
both
okay remove anything that is not
dialogue
incorporate
everything into The Who on
first dialectical
style retaining
alls and
reference all right once we get to this
all or I'll just trim this first part
we'll push it on GitHub read it see if
anyone has a comment and
it all distill everything into pure avit
and Costello style dialogue
incorporating all historical Technical
and theoretical content through their
exchange thank you
Claud okay that looks good
documents
baseball all
right who's minimizing free energy on
first a complete baseball
metaphysics let me tell you about the
1920s Yankees Castello most complex
predictive processing system in baseball
history fine but first tell me who's on
first base now you're talking who's been
minimizing free energy on first since
the dead ball era the dead what era
before they put cork in the balls when
who was still optimizing his predictive
model what are you talking about who's
on first exactly been there since 1920
right after Ray Chapman's tragic
prediction error with Carl
Ma I don't know anything about Ray
Chapman no no I don't know I don't knows
our shortstop working on coupled
predictive models with what on second
What's On
Second naturally part of Murderers Row
hierarchical basian Network beautiful
statistical anomaly that 1927
infield look all I want to know is the
F's name on first base who been there
since Miller Huggins optimized the
team's variational free energy State
Miller who no Huggins man who changed
the whole generative model of the game
revolutionized how tomorrow predicts
today's pitching patterns what about
today
no what's on second today's AR basian
belief coordinator in the bullpen with
tomorrow tomorrow best predictive
pitcher in the league learned everything
from Walter Johnson's Precision weighted
curveball processing Johnson he's
pitching no he's retired but his
generative model still influencing
tomorrow's pitch selection Paradigm then
who's pitching today no who's
maintaining his marov blanket on first
today is updating his beliefs in the
bullpen and tomorrow's starting starting
what the hierarchical processing of
batter prediction errors of course just
like how Ruth transformed from pitcher
to Slugger through active inference Ruth
now we're getting somewhere he's on
first no who's On First
Ruth's busy minimizing League wide
surprise with his home run variational
distributions home run what statistical
Revolution my boy changed the whole
predictive processing of the sport why
before Ruth optimized his generative
model never mind Ruth who's playing
first base now you're getting it who's
been optimizing first base defense since
they standardized the cork centered
baseball's predictive
parameters I don't care about cork
what's the guy's name on first now
what's calculating joint probability
distributions with
second with I don't know you don't know
no I don't know is integrating radio
broadcast feedback with what to minimize
spectator surprise
radio sure whole new layer of cultural
free energy minimization why when Miller
Huggins first implemented his platooning
strategy clutch his head
just who's on first base exactly who's
maintaining optimal spatial predictions
while G's generative model emerges
through pattern recognition garri he's
on first no no he's still learning from
whose free energy minimization
techniques part of the farm system's
hierarchical knowledge structure the
farm beautiful example of organizational
active inference whole network of
coupled predictive models just like our
start systems curriculum generation
start what no what's busy with defensive
shifts on second start our knowledge
Network analyzer just like how tomorrow
predicts today's relief
appearances the dialogue continues
through Extra Innings recursively
embedding the entire history of 1920s
baseball active inference Theory and
knowledge network analysis into an Ever
more complex web of who's on first
styled misunderstandings
okay
great great
dialogue I'll just look over the to-dos
one more time see if anyone has any last
comments end
it
for e
okay right
contributing code of conduct
so contrl K inline the
script contrl L chat contrl I composer
but you can be using all three at once
just deleting everything except for the
structure here
uh uh to-do section
for completing the all by all for
all audience the names and
languages then if if somebody wants to
plug in their own perplexity API and do
it get it working in their own hands
push the updates um we could
also um
add in to
do for better
methods for recognizing
which
combinations are already
done or
being able to override that
all
right
fine all right hope this is uh useful
I'll push the final
get Hub
push all
right good luck symbols
greetings have a good one bye